All right, I'm sorry I have to wrap up. Okay, בוקר טוב
*Boker Tov*. Today's דף *daf* is כ"ב *Chaf-Bet* and we are in
the middle of a fascinating discussion of a category I'm sure you
people have heard of, which is the issue of הסגת גבול hasagat
gvul, *Hasagas Gvul*, encroaching into somebody's
territory of פרנסה *parnassa*, which is an interesting sort of political issue
of
policy protectionism as opposed to free
market and do you want to protect certain individuals but how does
it ultimately help the general population and so on? So, that's the
issue that has come up in the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*. And the
position of רב הונא Rav Huna *Rav Huna* in the name of
רב Rav *Rav* said that if somebody already has a ריחיים *reychayim*,
a mill, going on in their מבוי mavoi, *mavoi*, which is actually
a larger neighborhood it's not even just the courtyard, you cannot open
up a competing mill in that מבוי mavoi, *mavoi* because he was
already there and you are unfairly competing with his business. One minute
and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* wants to know how does this fit
into the debate of the חכמים *Chachamim* and ר' יוסי *Reb Yosi*
about whether you have a store, I think it's ר' יוסי *Reb
Yosi*, right?
Where were we?
I'm sorry ר' יהודה *Reb Yehuda*, the debate of the חכמים *Chachamim*
and ר' יהודה *Reb Yehuda* that if two people have stores, is
one person allowed to give out free candy or nuts to the
kids, which will drive all the business to him. And there ר'
יהודה *Reb Yehuda* says that's not fair. I guess because you're not
really competing on the real basis of what you have to offer,
it's just a come-on. And the חכמים *Chachamim* say no, the other
person can do the same. So, that seems to be that ר'
יהודה *Reb Yehuda* is taking the position of trying to
protect the other store owner. So similarly his would be the position
to say you cannot open up a competing business. But the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* said they're not really comparable. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says they're not comparable in one direction. That according to the חכמים
*Chachamim*, the חכמים *Chachamim* maybe would be prepared to protect the business
owner who did not have a competing business, but here
they were both already there and the other person could do the
same type of strategy. Okay, but maybe otherwise they would be prepared
to protect the business owner to say somebody else can't open up
a competing business. What I said at the end of yesterday you
could also go the other way and you could say that even
ר' יהודה *Reb Yehuda* that wants to protect somebody against unfair business
practices, that's unfair business practices, opening up a competing business and sort
of leading the same way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* just a דף
*daf* before said קנאת kinat סופרים תרבה חכמה *kina soferim tarbe chochma*,
competition amongst teachers and amongst תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim, *talmidei chachamim* gets
everybody smarter, you could sort of say קנאת *kinas* business
owners gets the quality better and the prices better. So you could
actually make the split both ways. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
really saying that that is like a different type of an issue.
Yes, David, you had a question.
Yeah, it's more of a way to think about this that may
be helpful and that is that it's here because of property
rights. And so when the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is talking about these
הסגת גבול hasagat gvul *Hasagas Gvul* cases, it really is viewing it
as if you're moving the border mark.
And the point
is when do you own something
that you're expecting?
And the point is if you are so certain to get the
business, then that business is considered as if you already have it.
As a result taking it away is considered theft.
Like you're actually taking something from the person.
Exactly. And that's an important way because first of all I wonder
whether that may be the explanation to your question as to why
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't go in the other direction. Because if
you view ר' יהודה *Reb Yehuda*'s statement as one about theft, even
in that case that would be considered theft.
Then קל וחומר *kal vachomer* if the guy doesn't have a store.
Right, exactly. I very much appreciate that and that gets to the
question the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* earlier asked about how does this debate
fit in with the issue of can you spread a fishnet if
somebody else has staked out a location. And the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
said, well, maybe that's different because there he staked it out and
he got the fish to come there, like the fish are already
in his hand. And therefore that raises the question, how much do
you view customers as it were as something that you already own?
There was a real property thing, in the end you're going to
capture the fish. You don't take home the customers, but that's a
good way of thinking about it. Is it an issue of protecting
people and like a policy type, obviously that might be driving it,
but is it conceptualized that way? Or is it conceptualized as almost
a type of this is his already and you're taking it away?
Right.
How did you understand the measurement of כמלא ריצת הדג *kimlo ritzas
hadag*? Like how would you ever even...
Yeah, I have no idea when the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says עד
פרסה *ad parsa*, yeah, I don't know, I don't know. Okay, let's
go on though. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Okay. מיתיבי
*Meisvi*. So we are
about twenty lines from the bottom, it starts with the word בחיותי
*b'chayusi*, my livelihood. So then it says like this, מיתיבי *Meisvi*, I'll
ask you on this. עושה אדם חנות בצד חנותו של חברו *oseh
adam chanut b'tzad chanuto shel chaveiro*, you can open up a store.
like right near your friend's store, so ממש mamish competing, בצד חנותו
של חבירו, betzad chanuto shel chaveiro, ומרחץ בצד מרחצאו של חבירו, u'merchatz
betzad merchatzato shel chaveiro,
and a bath house right near his bath house. ואינו יכול למחות
בידו, ve'eino yachol limchot beyado, and the other guy cannot prevent you,
מפני שיכול לומר לו, mipnei sheyachol lomar lo, you can say because
you can say back to him, אתה עושה בתוך שלך ואני עושה
בתוך שלי, atah oseh betoch shelcha va'ani oseh betoch sheli, you're doing
what you want to do in your property, you're opening a store,
I'm doing what I want to do in my property, right? And
this also they were talking about the idea of property rights in
the sense of are you stealing something? But this also evokes, right,
how do we get to this? Because remember, part of what the
whole initial discussion was, can I basically plant a tree in my
yard and the roots are going to go and damage you? Can
I go ahead and plant like vegetables in my yard and it's
going to go and it's going to somehow damage your wall? So
here, it's like I can do whatever I want in my yard.
So I want to go ahead and I want to open a
store. I'm free to do that. Oh, it's going to indirectly take
away business from you? That's not my concern. Right? So on the
one hand, there are things you can stop. That's what we started
about the חצר, chatzer, that everybody in the חצר chatzer can agree
we don't want you to open up a store that's going to
bring in foot traffic. But when that's not the scenario, when it's
not like a certain type of a community that wants to maintain,
you know, as it were, zoning laws or certain ways of protecting
that whole community, if it's just another person and you're threatening me,
that's go back to the neighbor issue, not the חצר chatzer issue.
So you can say I'm doing what I want in my property.
So again, that phrasing echoes the things we've seen about things which
are other types of like physical damage. By the way, I do
want to say that economists have like studied this and again, I
only know this very superficially, but, you know, you would think like
in terms of הסגת גבול, hasagat gvul? like I've got a restaurant
here, the one kosher restaurant on the Upper West Side, so if
you want to open up a kosher restaurant, it has to be
somewhere else. You say don't open up on the Upper West Side,
it's going to compete. But actually, economists have found that when you
have multiple competing businesses in the same location, everybody does better because
then it drives all the traffic there. Oh, we can go to
this neighborhood, there are like four restaurants to choose from, you know,
and so actually, you know, that actually makes every... I mean again,
I'm sure it depends on circumstances, but if there's like a concentration,
then that becomes like the destination that everybody goes to and in
the end like it increases the traffic and the business for everyone.
There's a question I would have is would it be better if
the restaurants were had to be different restaurants?
Oh, right, that's an interesting point. Right, right, right, especially like restaurants,
you could have חלבי, chalavi, you could have בשרי. besari. Right, that's
a good point too. Right, right, because if they're ממש competing at
the same level and all the traffic's being driven there and one
is clearly better quality and better prices, unless of course there are
only so many seats. But yes, that's a good question. These both...
that's a good question in general in terms of you're right, in
terms of in terms of even if you פסקן pasken that there
is a problem of encroaching in somebody's business, right, what about if
you offer a something that's different, you know, and not different in
the way that you're only... one guy's only selling tea and the
other guy's only selling coffee and most people are either one or
the other. You know, different that people could still choose but you're
giving them a different type of a choice. You're not... right, that's
a good question.
And this this is something... must be some ancient wisdom to the
way this was set up. Like I've been to a שוק. shuk.
Like מחנה יהודה Machane Yehuda is like nothing compared to...
Right, that's an excellent example. מחנה יהודה Machane Yehuda is an excellent
example.
Right. Ten thousand סמטאות simtaot in this שוק, shuk, this bazaar, and
you go for five square blocks, they're all selling sandals. And then
in the next five square blocks, they're all butchers. And they're all
concentrated... and they're all thriving.
You're right. מחנה יהודה Machane Yehuda is a great example of that.
You're right.
Okay, so anyway, but the...
isn't some of the ועד vaad here to control like the restaurants,
like in Riverdale? Doesn't work.
The ועד? vaad? Yeah, I mean, that's what you have. That places
that give הכשרים, hechsherim, you know, use these sort of giving of
הכשרים hechsherim as a way of enforcing these הסגת גבול rules. The
question is also it becomes a question, are they is are they
always following like the הלכות halachot of הסגת גבול? Or, you know,
and and it can become a lot... it can as you can
imagine, because it's sometimes very, very contentious around those issues. You know,
I remember growing up, you know, where I came from, there were
those types of issues and a lot of the consumers felt that
it was like limiting their choices and just encouraging things to be
poor quality, you know, and so on. So it raises those important
questions. But you're right, it plays up today even up until today,
particularly in cases of restaurants where you can control it by whether
you're going to give a השגחה. hashgacha. Sometimes they bring in an
outside השגחה. hashgacha. Fine, you don't want to give me the local
השגחה, hashgacha, I'll get OU, I'll get HK, or something like that.
Yeah, on the other hand, in a community like where I come
from, where it's a sort of isolated community,
what we found is every time a second butcher store opened, there
wasn't enough traffic to support two, so they both had problems. And
the time frame that you would need to get the population to
grow that would support the
business was too long.
That's a very good point.
Right, if there's if you're serving a limited community and there's a
limited need, and then you're right, then... so all these parameters seem
that they should be relevant.
Yes, and in one of
the
communities not too far from me, there's an issue like this with
חב"ד. Chabad. Uh-huh. Open being like literally two meters away from... Yeah,
these are all really good, really important issues. Okay, so let's continue
now in the גמרא. Gemara
Okay. תנאי. Tanai. It's a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. דתניא, Detanya, we
taught in a ברייתא. braitah. You know, and nowadays of course we
have a much greater sensitivity to it when it's about mom and
pop stores versus like these big, you know, corporations, like yeah, you
want to have a little bookstore and you know Barnes and Noble
moves in, right? That really raises other issues. Okay. Amazon, right, Amazon
moves in everywhere. Okay, no הלכה halacha is global on the internet,
which is a challenge. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
תנאי. Tanai. Anyway, so how could רב יהודה אמר רב Rav Yehuda
amar Rav say that it's a problem, here you've got a ברייתא,
braitah, I'm sorry, not רב יהודה אמר רב, Rav Yehuda amar Rav,
רב Rav הונא says this, here you have a ברייתא braitah that
says you're allowed to open up a competing business. So the גמרא
Gemara says תנאי, tanai, thank you so much, it's a debate of
תנאים. Tannaim. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braitah, כופין בני
מבואות זה את זה שלא להושיב ביניהם לא חייט ולא בורסקי ולא
מלמד תינוקות. Kofin benei mavo'ot zeh et zeh shelo lehoshiv beneihem lo
chayat velo bursaki velo melamed tinokot. So this is what we saw
the other day, a מבוי, mavoi now here it has the phrase
מבוי, mavoi, before we saw the חצר, chatzer, but an entire מבוי
mavoi. can agree that we want to limit, now this is not
competition, we want to limit the foot traffic. So nobody is allowed
to open up a tailor business here, a tanner, a tannery, or
a schoolhouse. We discussed the schoolhouse issue before.
Right? So that's to protect the foot traffic. ולא אחד מבני בעלי
אומניות. Velo echad mibnei ba'alei umaniyot.
And nobody can open up like one of their, you know, little
craft store in their location, again to sell, because the משנה Mishnah
already tells us you're allowed to make this stuff in your house.
ולשכינו אינו כופהו. Ul'shcheno eino kofeh'u.
Now that's true that you can also sort of agree within this
courtyard, within this neighborhood, whatever, this is residential zoning, not commercial zoning.
Okay? But, I'm sorry, let me just check רש"י Rashi for a
second, I want to make sure I explain that correctly. No, I'm
sorry, I'm sorry, I was confusing it with the thing before. רש"י
Rashi says the key of להושיב ביניהם lehoshiv beneihem is that you
cannot bring in an outside business person. Okay, so somebody, you can
say, so this is all about the competition issue, right, excuse me,
not about the foot traffic. So you can basically say we want
to keep outsiders away from opening businesses here. Okay? So you know,
to maybe it's motivated by the foot traffic issue, who knows what
it's motivated by, but that's okay to say this is our space
and therefore it's our space the same way you can keep somebody
off of your yard, everybody who collectively owns the מבוי, mavoi. you
know, can basically keep certain people away from the מבוי. mavoi These
people are going to now ahead, you know, we don't want those
businesses opened up. But, let's say it's not an outsider, let's say
it's somebody who has rights here, let's say it's somebody who lives
in the מבוי. mavoi, So then you can't stop them from opening
this
store. ולשכינו אינו כופהו, Ul'shcheno eino kofeh'u, you cannot stop them. Okay?
So I guess the question here is also why can't you stop
them because of the foot traffic, but this might be one of
those things that is not a lot of foot traffic, right? Let
me see, hold on, I'm sorry.
Because they own the מבוי mavoi and as opposed to...
Oh, oh, that's also a good point, maybe because it's a מבוי,
mavoi. you're right, it's a מבוי mavoi so people are traveling in
the street as well. That also might be the case, correct. And
some of these things are ones we hadn't had before, I don't
think we had before
a tailor
or a
tanner, so I don't know, maybe those things have less foot traffic,
but what David said could very much be correct as well, it's
a מבוי. mavoi, All right, so the point is you can keep
certain people out of the מבוי mavoi. from coming from the outside,
it's your space, but somebody wants to open a business like this,
you can't stop them from doing it. And for some reason we're
not concerned with the foot traffic issue either. Okay, so that's point
number one. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר אף לשכינו כופהו. Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel omer, af lshcheno kofeh'u. No,
you can stop your neighbor from doing it. Now why is that?
So רש"י Rashi says, I mean whatever, or the גמרא Gemara seems
to be interpreting it that we're talking about the fact that you
are have the same business. Okay? And that's the issue. So and
therefore so the גמרא Gemara is reading this as a debate not
about stopping foot traffic like the משנה, Mishnah, but about stopping a
competing business. So it's a debate of תנאים, Tannaim, can you stop
somebody from opening a competing business who has a right to be
here. אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Amar Rav Huna brei de-Rav
Yehoshua, פשיטא לי, pshita li, now it's obvious to me, בר מתא
בר מתא אחריתא מצי מעכב, bar mata bar mata achrita matzi me'akev,
that if you're from one town, you can stop somebody from a
different town from again opening up a certain type of a business.
Again, similar idea, it's your town and you're allowed to sort of
say you know you can't from the outside come ahead and do
this.
However, ואי שייך בכרגא דהכא לא מצי מעכב. ve'ei shayich becharga dehacha
lo matzi me'akev. However,
let's say they all pay the same tax to the same crown,
to the same you know same municipality, then they're not considered to
be from the outside. Now again what the ראשונים Rishonim explain is,
you can still say we're not letting you in. into our courtyard,
we're not letting you into our מבוי, mavoi but let's say it's
a place that he's not encroaching on anybody's courtyard or מבוי. mavoi
He's got his pushcart, he stands in the middle of the street,
he sells it there, right? It's a place that it's accessible to
the public, it's not a private space. Alright, so in that type
of a case, so again, this is
the—you cannot keep them out of selling and you can't say you're
not, you know, you don't have that right in this town because
he is considered to be part of the town. Now, בר מבוי
לבר מבוי דנפשיה לא מצי מעכב. bar mavoi l'bar mavoi d'nafsheih lo
matzi m'akev. Now, he says it was obvious also to me that
sort of against Rav Huna's teaching, that if everybody shares a מבוי
mavoi? and you're not an outsider, so once you're not an outsider,
you're allowed to open up a certain business in the מבוי mavoi?
and it doesn't matter if it's a competing business. Okay, so as
long as you have a right to be here, you are, you
can open up a competing business. That's the basic point. But here's
the one thing I don't know. בעי רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע
בר מבוי לבר מבוי אחרינא מאי? ba'ei Rav Huna breih d'Rav Yehoshua
bar mavoi l'bar mavoi achrina mai? How about if opening up a
competing business in a different מבוי? mavoi. All right, so what's the
scope? Right? What we're sort of saying is is that you've got
a—let me just double check. Like a franchise?
You open up several shops?
Well, you open up a competing store, shop.
But he belongs in the town so those pay taxes and stuff.
Right. But he's trying to open up the
shop in the next מבוי? mavoi, In the next מבוי. mavoi, Yeah.
In the next. You
live in different מבוי, mavoi, we live in different מבוי, mavoi. you've
got a store in your מבוי, mavoi
I want to open up a competing store in your מבוי.
mavoi, Okay, and it's not like I'm selling almonds and you're selling
wool. No, it's the exact same thing. Right. Right, it's peanuts, both
of them.
Right. Right. Right, so the funny thing here is is that when
you think about the competition idea, the more you're close, the more
you're שכנא, shacheina, you're opening it in nearby, the more competition presumably
you're presenting. On the same, on the other hand, here the point
is is that you can't, you can prevent somebody because you say
they don't belong here. But if they belong here, they're a שכנא,
shacheina, then they have a right to do it. Okay, so it's
almost like the reverse, I mean in terms of the competition it
represents, it presents greater competition possibly because they're right nearby, but because
they belong here, you can't prevent them. And the question is if
somebody from this מבוי mavoi, over here wanted to enter into this
מבוי, mavoi right, and sell, so do you sort of say that
because they're all sort of like... He's opening it in his own?
Well, I don't understand, see that's what I'm trying to figure out.
If he's opening it in his own מבוי, mavoi, how can, so,
and I'm opening it here in this מבוי mavoi, and I have
a right in this מבוי, mavoi you have a right in this
מבוי, mavoi? how could you in this מבוי mavoi. stop me doing
what I want in my מבוי? mavoi If you already have... Yes,
but you can't even stop your neighbor from opening up a competing
business.
Right, if I'm next door, I can open up the same shop.
Exactly, if you can't stop your neighbor from opening it up because
they have a right to be here, certainly you can't stop somebody
in this other מבוי. mavoi I know, but that's what I was
sort of struggling with because it becomes a little weird. Anyway, but
that seems to be the point. Can we keep out, you know,
people from other, from the other מבוי from opening this type of
a business? We can keep out people from another city from coming
in, from another town from coming in, but you're all part of
the same town and you're going to open it up on a
מבוי which is a semi-public space, right, are you allowed to say
you're not allowed to do it? So that he doesn't know. תיקו.
teiku. אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef, ומודה רב הונא. u'modeh Rav
Huna. Now Rav Huna, who is more strict on this and says
that, you know, you can prevent somebody from doing it even if
they have a right to be here, he agrees במקרי דרדקי דלא
מצי מעכב. b'makrei dardakei d'lo matzi m'akev. Ah, getting back to the
school children, the רב should be very happy. We're not, we're never
leaving education. Okay, yes, you can open up a competing school even,
you know, even if you generally cannot open up a competing business,
a competing school you can open up. Why? דאמר מר. d'amar mar.
Okay, so people take out that next line. דאמר מר קנאת סופרים
תרבה חכמה. d'amar mar kinat sofrim tarbeh chochmah.
Yes, we actually do care about competition is going to be good,
you know, when it comes to Torah, even if in other places,
you know, there's an issue of, like again, קנאת anybody gets quality
better and the prices down, but you know, there there might be
other considerations, protecting people's income and as David said, it might be
a type of a theft. But here the aspect of getting the
best quality education is an overriding value and that basically wins out,
similar to how in the משנה Mishna you can't prevent people, you
can prevent people from opening up businesses that are going to increase
foot traffic but not schools. Education is an overriding value and it
trumps all these other concerns. Yes.
But don't you think, do you think it's striking at all that
this principle does not apply to economics, you know, קנאת רוכלים? kinat
rochlim?
I just
said that, I said that, yes, competition always is better for the
consumer, except of course in the cases, you know, that was being
mentioned, like if there's not enough of a base to support two
businesses, but competition is better for the consumer, but there are other
considerations, right? There's protecting somebody's livelihood, it might be considered a type
of theft, other points that we've made. So this value is there,
but the point was when it comes to Torah,
this... Is there a formulation of that?
Like right, right, right, right.
קנאת סופרים *Kinat sofrim* מרבה *marbe* the quality, the cost ratio.
Yes.
Was it common in those days for someone who lived in one
courtyard to go shopping in another?
I really have no idea.
But the question I would have is if you liked a merchant
in another courtyard and thought his stuff was really great, right, then
you wanted him to be in your courtyard because it was easier.
Could you convince him to come in?
I really don't know. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says
like this: ומודה *umodeh*, okay, אמר amar, רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak. *amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak*, ומודה רב הונא *umodeh
Rav Huna*. Now again רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע Rav Huna breih
de-Rav Yehoshua, *Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua*, רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע
*Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua* who is the one who tries to
be more protecting of the existing businesses, he agrees that Dove mentioned
רוכלין *rochlin*, ברוכלין המחזירים בעיירות דלא מצי מעכב *berochlin hamachzirim ba'ayarot dalo
matzi me'akev*. One thing that you have a right to do is
if you've got local shops here that sell various wares and you've
got these רוכלין *rochlin* who tend to sell whatever fragrances. Even if
you have a Chanel No. 5 shop in your neighborhood, you're allowed
these fragrance sellers, these itinerant fragrance sellers to come in and to
sell their fragrances. Why? And that's not considered to be, you don't
have a right to keep them out, you're not part of this
town, you don't have a right, you're competing against local business. Why?
דאמר מר עזרא תיקן להם לישראל שיהו רוכלין מחזירים בעיירות כדי שיהו
תכשיטים מצויין לבנות ישראל Yisrael *de'amar mar Ezra tiken lahem l'Yisrael sheyehu
rochlin machzirim ba'ayarot kedei sheyehu tachshitim metzuyan livnot Yisrael*. So they sell
fragrances and jewelry and the whole thing. So again talking about a
type of overriding concerns. The same way there's overriding concerns of quality
of education, there's overriding concerns about these selling these types of things
to make it very available for the women.
So this is one of Ezra's major תקנות *takanot*.
It is, right. Okay, yep. והני מילי *vehani mili*, and then we
also said, והני מילי *vehani mili* לאהדורי le'ahadurei. *le'ahaduri*. Now that is
only to pass through. אבל לקבוע *aval likboa*, one of these
itinerant merchants decides hey this is good business in this town I'm
just going to park here for the next while, so then that's
not acceptable. Then that is competing business from an outside town. אבל
לאהדורי אפילו אבל לאקבועי לא *aval le'ahaduri afilu aval le'akvei lo*. ואי
צורבא מרבנן היא *ve'ee tzurba me'rabanan hee*, now if the guy's a
תלמיד חכם talmid chacham *talmid chacham* this merchant who's going from town
to town, אפילו לאקבועי נמי *afilu le'akvei nami*, then you can even
make establish yourself here even if you come from the outside. כי
הא דרבא שרא להו לרב יאשיה ולרב עובדיה לקבוע דלא כהלכתא *kee
ha de'Rava shara lehu le'Rav Yoshiya ule'Rav Ovadia likboa dalo kehilchata*, and
like רבא Rava. *Rava* allowed רב יאשיה *Rav Yoshiya* and רב עובדיה
*Rav Ovadia* to establish a shop in the town that they were
not of the towns-people, they came from the outside, even though that's
not really the הלכה halacha, *halacha*. The town is really allowed to
protect against that. מאי טעמא *mai ta'ama*? כיון דרבנן נינהו אתו לטרדומי
מגירסייהו *keivan derabanan ninhu atu letirdumei migirsaihu*. Because they are rabbis, if
you make them go from town to town or whatever, they're going
to have very little chance to learn תורה Torah *Torah*. So in
order for the quality of תלמוד תורה Torah *talmud Torah*, we gave
them an advantage.
Now obviously that raises some interesting questions that reminds us of an
earlier discussion about how the rabbis don't have to pay tax because
they're learning
תורה Torah *Torah*. And if you want to just frame it הלכתית
*halachically* also, whatever happens to not to make תורה *Torah* a קרדום
לחפור בו *kardom lachpor bo*, make תורה *Torah* as a means of
gaining personal
financial advantage.
So רש"י Rashi *Rashi*'s an interesting רש"י Rashi *Rashi* on this, רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* says דלא כהלכתא *dalo kehilchata*, if you look down in
רש"י *Rashi* like six lines down in the narrow lines, אלא לפנים
משורת הדין *ela lifnim mishurat hadin*, which is a very interesting application
of the principle לפנים משורת הדין *lifnim mishurat hadin* because לפנים משורת
הדין *lifnim mishurat hadin* normally is not coming like I'm the one
that's supposed to do לפנים משורת הדין *lifnim mishurat hadin* and give
up on my rights and entitlements for the sake of doing the
right thing to the other person. So here it's like פוסקנין *paskening*
לפנים משורת הדין *lifnim mishurat hadin* for the townspeople. You the town,
I mean I don't know if that's what רש"י *Rashi* meant, he
meant like לפנים משורת הדין *lifnim mishurat hadin* it sounds like רש"י
*Rashi* I'm going to do לפנים משורת הדין *lifnim mishurat hadin* for
these rabbis, right? But you're doing it at other people's expense. So
what you're really sort of saying is the town should do לפנים
משורת הדין *lifnim mishurat hadin* for these rabbis and they should be
prepared to give up their rights because of a way of supporting
תורה *Torah*. You're פוסקנין *paskening* for them. Exactly. You're פוסקנין *paskening* that
for the town, right. So that is very interesting. Okay so now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has the
following question about going in the army I guess.
Right well the army we discussed when the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* spoke
about תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim. *talmidei chachamim* getting out of taxes and
paying for the walls because our תורה *Torah* protects us, how that
played into the whole הסדר *Hesder* discussions and so on. Yeah we
discussed that. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: הני
דיקולי
*hanei dikulei*, now these various like what are they, basket, wicker basket
sellers רש"י *Rashi* says, דאייתו דיקולי לבבל *de'ayitu dikulei le'Bavel*, they brought
their baskets their wares to בבל *Bavel* from the outside. So again
everybody agrees whether רב הונא *Rav Huna* or whatever that you're allowed
to keep outsiders from bringing in outside competing business. So they came
אתו בני מחוזא Mechuza. קא מעכבי עלייהו *atu benei Mechuza ka me'akvei
aleihu*. So the people of the town said, "No, we don't want
to let you sell this, you're competing with our local businesses." They
came to רבינא,
he said to them, מאלמא אתו ולאלמא ליזבנו, Me'alma ato ule'alma lizbenu,
they came from out there and they can sell. Now you could
have read this: let them sell out there, don't sell here. But
that's not the way it's reading. It's reading: they came from the
general population and therefore they can sell to the general population. Which
means, as we're about to see, they can sell at a time
of a market day when people from the larger general population are
gathering. It's not like it's something that's local to this town that
you're seen as like taking away the business of these townspeople. At
a time when it's open to a larger population, then that's who
they're selling to. They're not דוקא davka taking away business from the
local business. So the גמרא Gemara spells that out in the next
line. Where were we? אתו לקמיה דרבינא, Ato lekamei d'Ravina, okay, ולאלמא
ליזבנו, ule'alma lizbenu, והני מילי ביומא דשוקא. vehanei milei beyoma d'shuka.
That's only on the market day. Because then it's seen as a
time
when the customers are not only the local townspeople. אבל בלא יומא
דשוקא לא. Aval belo yoma d'shuka lo. But if it's not the
market day, then no, then you are taking away from the local
businesses. וביומא דשוקא נמי לא אמרן, Uveyoma d'shuka nami lo amran, and
we also don't say it on a market day, אלא לזבוני בשוקא,
ella lizbonei beshuka,
they're only allowed on the market to sell in the market. אבל
לאהדורי לא. Aval le'ahadurei lo. But to go door to door, no,
they're not allowed. And you could actually understand this, right? The local
town initially starts to have a market day on whatever Sunday. They're
not planning on having it for the surrounding neighborhoods, but it's the
biggest town in the area and there's a lot of business that's
getting done on Sunday. So all of a sudden the people from
the surrounding towns start going there, and the merchants from the surrounding
towns start going there, and they want to sell their wares there
on that day. So in that type of scenario,
you're allowed to. You could understand from the perspective of the townspeople,
they want to have just their merchants sell to the bigger population.
But once the bigger population is coming, then you have to allow
those outside sellers to participate as well.
No fuller brush men. Exactly.
All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says, by the way, you
know, it is interesting. This comes up a lot in
these...
That's already covered by the earlier... You can't go door to door.
Right. That's the issue. You have to go in the שוק shuk
and set it up on the יומא דשוקא, yoma d'shuka, they can't
go לאהדורי.
Right.
What about as a תקנה? takkanah? That was specifically רוכלים, rochlim, that
was specifically
perfumes and jewelry.
I don't know where brushes would fit in. Anyway. All right. Anyway.
Moving on. Moving on. So but I did want to make a
point, though, an important I think
point about thinking about our own sort of acts of consumerism and
so on is that, you know, in local
Jewish towns, it's often likely that you'll have a local storekeeper, right?
So we got a guy here who sells fish, kosher fish. So
you could just as easily go to Key Food or whatever and
buy the fish. I mean, question if it's already filleted, can you
identify the fish? But if it's not filleted, or if it's whatever,
salmon or whatever, that you can identify it even if it's filleted
or whatever. So you can go to Key Food, right? Should you
go to the local business owner to support your local Jewish business?
It's not exactly the same, but conceptually it is, if you think
about it like a Jewish community has store people and then there's
people that, I mean, we live in an integrated community, right? This
local ספרים sefarim guy, you know, I'm sure you go on Amazon
and get the stuff cheaper, but do you דוקא davka make a
point of supporting your local businesses?
So, you know, I mean, my wife who is such a צדקת,
tzadeket, she wants us to do this, not דוקא davka about Jewish
businesses, like rather than ordering some hardware thing
on whatever, some kind of doorknobs or light bulbs or whatever, rather
than going to Staples or ordering on Amazon, she wants us to
go to the local hardware guy. No, she's right. She always keeps
me on the straight and narrow, my wife.
Everybody should support ישראל Yisrael, in this community. It's very important.
We're not talking about ישראל, Yisrael, this wasn't about ישראל, Yisrael. this
was just about a local business.
I was talking about the person named ישראל.
Oh, he's the guy who owns Larry's the locksmith. Oh, Riverdale Judaica.
Okay. All right. Moving on. Okay. So now the גמרא says like
this. Okay. So, by the way, very important תוספות, Tosafot, I want
to read you a very, it's always great when he brings in
the
historical application. Look at תוספות. Tosafot. He says like this, מאלמא אתו
ולאלמא ליזבנו. Me'alma ato ule'alma lizbenu.
This is about selling, an outsider selling at a market day. So
he says, מכאן משמע דביומא דשוקא היה מותר להלוות לבני אדם הבאים
ממקומות שם לשוק מנכרים דאתו
מעלמא. Mikan mashma d'beyoma d'shuka haya mutar lehalvot livnei adam habaim mimkomot
sham lashuk minocharim d'ato me'alma. So תוספות' Tosafot main business was lending
money. All right. So here's a market day. So you know when
you have a market day, you know right now in the big
super malls, they all have... these ATM machines, right? So anyway, so
one of the things people would come for the markets is they'd
want to borrow money, not just to buy at the market, but
you know this is the day that everybody's buying and selling, so
that's also where you find all the money lenders that are there
that are prepared to lend you money. So תוספות Tosafos says so
if you're from a neighboring town, can you go to a different
town on their market day to loan your money to the non-Jews
with interest? Okay. להלוות לבני אדם הבאים ממקומות שם לשוק ולנכרים דאתו
מעלמא. lehalvos livne adam habaim mekomos sham leshuk ulenochrim deato mealma.
So he says you can sell it to non-Jews that come from
outside of town, אבל לבני מקום לא, aval livne makom lo, and
but not to those of that town, ודווקא בשוקא אבל אדורי לא.
vedavka beshuka aval adure lo. Also number one, you can only do
open up your sort of your your mini bank there in the
marketplace. You cannot go to you know door to door or pursue
people outside of the marketplace on that day of the marketplace. But
the interesting thing also about תוספות Tosafos is it sounds like תוספות,
Tosafos, you've opened up your business on a market day. If somebody
comes from that town that you know they're from their town, it
sounds from תוספות Tosafos you're supposed to turn them away. Though when
the גמרא says לעלמא ליזבני, lealma lizbeni, it doesn't just mean today
is a day that the larger population is here, you can sell
to anyone, right? It sounds like you can sell to people who
are not from this town, which is a much more narrow read,
right? You see how תוספות Tosafos says you're allowed to sell ולנכרים
דאתו מעלמא ulenochrim deato mealma to the non-Jews lend money who came
from outside the town, אבל לבני מקום לא. aval livne makom lo.
So it's actually a more limiting read of this גמרא. You can
only sell to the outsiders.
But how do you make sure that people can't the residents can't
buy from the outsiders? Because how's the outsider going to know who's
the resident of the town and who's not?
Right, that's true. I assume it means that if you know or
you've been told by the town's people, right, or something like that.
Okay, but רש״י Rashi did not read it necessarily you know in
that limiting way. All right, now the גמרא continues.
Okay. הנהו אמלוראי, hanu amlorai, these sellers of of a of a
what a wool, thank you, wool, right? דאיתו אימרא לפום נהרא, deaisu
imra lefum nahara,
they brought wool to the to the river bank here, ואתו בני
מאתא קא מעכבי עלייהו, veasu bne masai kama akvi alaivahu,
so the people of the town said, "We don't want you selling,
you're competing with our local business." אתו לקמיה דרב כהנא, asu lekame
deRav Kahana, they came to רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. אמר להו דינא
הוא דמעכבי עלייכו. amar lehu dina hu demaakvi alaichu. They have a
right to prevent you from selling here. אמרו ליה אית לן אשראי.
amru le islan ashrai.
They said, "Wait a minute, but we have we have people who
owe us money, we've extended credit to people in this city." So
and therefore we're here also to collect our debts. So so what
are we supposed to do? Like and you know have our you
know lose money while we're working to get our to collect our
debts? We we need to sort of keep our you know sell
our sell our wares. So so he said, אזל ואמרו ליה דינא,
azal veamru le dina, so he said to them, זילו זבנו שיר
חיותייכו, zilu zivnu shir chyusaichu, fine,
you can sell as you know the amount that it requires to
basically earn a living. You can't be making a big profit, but
the amount you need to pay for your hotel bill and your
food or whatever while you're here, that you can sell. עד דאקריתו
אשראיכו ושקלו, ad deakrisu ashraichu vesilu, until you get your debts paid
off and then you get and then get out of here. All
right. Which is interesting, right? I mean again, who makes who gets
you know it's a little bit similar to the case about the
תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim. which is is that the rights of the
towns people are not absolute. We have to also consider they fundamentally
do have a right to to get competing businesses can't operate here,
but sometimes we have to be considerate about the needs of the
individuals that are coming. So you know there's one type of a
thing about giving them a special permission because they're תלמידי חכמים. The
other thing is look נבך, nebach, people have to have a right
to be able to go to the town and collect their debts
and therefore not you know and they have to be able to
keep on earning a living while they're doing that. So how do
you find like how are you able to strike that type of
a balance? Okay. So again you know what do you do I
meaning the point I'm saying is you see this sort of weighing
but you don't see any hard rules and you know there're going
to be other cases that are more complex than this, right? There's
a lot of competing factors and how exactly to strike the balance.
Yes. Is it אשראי ashrai credit or a debt? Yes.
No, we've sold to people on credit and now therefore we have
to collect the money that they owe us. Right. I I might
have said debt but I meant it would because of goods that
were sold on credit to these people. So now we need to
we're here to collect that to collect our invoices. Right. Yes.
That means they've already sold in this community before if they had
if people owe them money from the...
Right, so I was wondering about that. I'm meaning they came to
our stores and you know and now in the other town. I
was wondering about that. How did they extend that credit in the
first place? Right. Okay. Yeah. Right, because כרטיס אשראי kartis ashrai is
a credit card. Yeah. So okay.
Okay. רב דימי מנהרדעא אייתו גרוגרות בספינה, Rav Dimi miNharde'a aisu grogrois
besfina,
he brought these pressed figs, right, is that right? I always get
it wrong. Figs, right. Dried figs in a boat. אמר ליה ריש
גלותא לרבא פוק חזי. Amar le resh galusa leRava puk chazi. Go
find out, go test him. אי צורבא מרבנן הוא נקיט ליה שוקא.
ee tzorba merabanan hu nakit le shuka. So go find out, go
test him, see if he's a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham... and if
he's a תלמיד חכם... talmid chacham chacham, then he can have a
right to sell from the outside, okay? This is again this special,
this special advantage or allowance given to תלמידי חכמים. Okay, so
now Rashi goes even further. Rashi says נקיטו ליה שוקא nakeit lei
shuka is הכריז שלא ימכור איש בעיר גרוגרות אלא הוא. hachriz she-lo
yimkor ish ba-ir grogros ela hu.
He should have the sole monopoly of selling in this city, which
is like I don't know, maybe because of the phrase to be
נקיט שוקא nakeit shuka is different than the phrase before, but it's
already one thing to allow him to sell and now actually saying
that he should be the sole seller. Okay, so Rava said to
where were we? At length my, oh
so ריש גלותא Resh Galuta said that to רבא. Rava? Okay, so
אמר ליה רבא לרב אדא בר אהבה, amar lei Rava le-Rav Adda
bar Ahava, Abba, so Rava gave this assignment to Rav Adda bar
Ahava, his student: פוק טעמי ליה בקנקניה. puk taamei lei be-kankanei.
Go smell his barrel, his like his bottle, his bottle of wine,
meaning to say when you open a wine and you smell it
to see how good it is. So that was a metaphor used
to go, go give him a פארהער, faher, go test him to
see if he's a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham. or not.
And when you say לבדוק בקנקנו של מישהו, livdok be-kankano shel mishehu,
it's to look at his insides, see what he's, oh yeah?
That's a modern Israeli phrase? Aha,
interesting, interesting. So that's exactly this. Very interesting. I didn't know that
it made it to modern Hebrew. Okay, נפיק אזל בעא מיניה. nafik
azal baei minei. So Rav Adda bar Ahava went and he tested
him. He said פילא שבלע כפיפה
מצרית. pila she-bala kfifa mitzrit. It's such an interesting question to ask
him. Like he figures like I'm going to ask him the hardest
question possible, see how good of a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham So
he says, if an elephant swallows a wick a, an Egyptian wicker
basket והקיאה דרך בית הרעי ve-hikaah derech beit ha-rei
and then he excreted it, so מהו? mahu? What's the story? Is
it, can you make and then apparently the way תוספות Tosafot explains
it is you then want to make a vessel out of the
wickers that came out, out of the, you know, that had transformed.
So if it's, you make, if it's a wicker vessel, so then
it's מקבל טומאה. mikabel tumah. But if it's a vessel made out
of excrement, then it's not מקבל טומאה. mikabel tumah. So what would
be its status? And somehow surprisingly לא הוה בידיה. lo hava bideih.
He didn't happen to have the answer off the top of his
head.
So אמר ליה, amar lei, he said
to him, אמר ליה, amar lei,
מר ניהו רבא? Mar nihu Rava? So,
oh, I'm sorry, so רב דימי, Rav Dimi, okay, so he didn't
know. So then, so then רב דימי Rav Dimi said to רב
אדא, Rav Adda, so רב דימי Rav Dimi was the one with
the pressed figs and רב אדא Rav Adda was the one testing
him. So after רב דימי Rav Dimi was שוואגד shvagd up by
רב אדא, Rav Adda, he said to him, are you רבא? Rava.
Because he didn't know, he was new to the town. He knew
there was the biggest תלמיד חכם talmid chacham, was רבא. Rava This
was רבא's Rava? student, right? Who was testing him, but he didn't
know that. So
מר ניהו רבא? Mar nihu Rava? Are you רבא? Rava, So טפח
ליה בסנדליה. tapach lei be-sandaleih.
So רב אדא Rav Adda like kicked him. Now it could mean
he kicked him with his sandal, like or you know or even
like hit him with his sandal. But רש"י says that what it
means is that he kicked him on his sandal, meaning meaning not
that he used his sandal to kick him or to hit him
on the head with it, but that he kicked him on, you
know, he, he kicked his foot, he kicked him on his sandal.
Right, exactly. So אמר ליה בין דידי לרבא איכא טובא. amar lei
bein didi le-Rava ika tuva.
So רב אדא Rav Adda said, look, between me and רבא, Rava.
I don't get close to רבא. Rava Between me and רבא Rava,
there's a huge gap. מיהו על כרחך אנא רבך ורבא רבה דרבך.
mihu al korchacha ana ravach ve-Rava raba de-ravach.
But you know, between the implicit point being, but between me and
you there's also a large gap in the other direction. So you
know, I'm not רבא, Rava רבא's Rava my Rebbe and you and
I, you know,
and and רבא Rava is your Rebbe's Rebbe, meaning he's my Rebbe,
okay? I'm your Rebbe. לא נקיטו ליה שוקא. lo nakeitu lei shuka.
So they said you're not a big enough תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham,
we're not going to give you a special permission to sell. פסדו
גרוגרות דידיה. psadu grogros dideih. So all of his, all of his
figs got spoiled.
This is רב דימי's Rav Dimi figs. אתא לקמיה דרב יוסף. ata
le-kameih de-Rav Yosef. So רב דימי Rav Dimi came to רב יוסף,
Rav Yosef, to the one who was bringing the figs. אמר ליה
חזי מר מאי עבדו בי. amar lei chazi Mar mai avdu bi.
Did you see what they did to me? They tested me, they
kicked me on the sandal, they said they wouldn't let me sell
my stuff. אמר ליה מאן דלא שיהא לאוניסא דמלכא דאדום, amar lei
man de-la sheya le-unisa de-malka de-Edom, the person who did not sort
of hold back his,
you know for, אמר ליה מאן דלא שיהא לאוניסא דמלכא דאדום, amar
lei man de-la sheya le-unisa de-malka de-Edom, God, excuse me, God, the
one who did not hold back
defending the, the affliction of the king of Edom, the way he
was sort of embarrassed, לא נשהא לאוניסך. lo nish-ha le-unisach.
He will not hold back avenging, you know, your, the way you've
been mistreated. דכתיב, de-chtiv, where do we see God did not hold
back avenging the mistreatment of the king of Edom? כה אמר השם
על שלשה פשעי מואב ועל ארבעה לא אשיבנו על שרפו עצמות מלך
אדום לסיד, koh amar Hashem al shlosha pishei Moav ve-al arbaah lo
ashivenu al sarpo atzmot melech Edom la-sid, for three sins of Moab
and for four I will not hold back
because they burned his bones into plaster. So even the king of
Edom even after his death, because of the way they disrespected him,
God is going to punish. So God should come and defend your
honor. So נח נפשיה דרב אדא
בר אבא.
Nach Nafshei d'Rav Ada
bar Abba.
So רב אדא בר אבא Rav Ada bar Abba died. רב אדא
בר
אבא Rav Ada bar Abba was the one who, you know, who
had this exchange with רב דימי Rav Dimi and kicked רב דימי
Rav Dimi and spoke to him in a, you know, maybe in
a, you know, in a disrespectful derogatory way. So נח נפשיה דרב
אדא בר אבא. Nach Nafshei d'Rav Ada bar Abba. רב יוסף Rav
Yosef אמר, amar, now רב יוסף Rav Yosef said, אנא ענישתי, Ana
Nishtei, oy, he died, it was my fault that he died. They're
not taking credit, they're taking the blame. You know, they're each one,
you know, he's basically saying, oy, I spoke too soon, you know,
now I caused his death. אנא ענישתי Ana Nishtei דאנא לטייתיה, d'ana
latyei, I cursed him. רב דימי Rav Dimi מנהרדעא mi-Nehardea אמר, amar,
now רב דימי, Rav Dimi, who's the one who had the pressed
figs, he said, אנא ענישתי, Ana Nishtei,
no, I'm to blame, דאפסי גרוגרות דידי, d'afsi grogaros didi, which is
fascinating. Why am I to blame? Because it was because I brought
my figs that this whole event happened and therefore he mistreated me
and I came to complain and therefore I'm to blame, right? Now,
of course, sometimes we think that way, right? Something bad happens, you
know, and
you ask somebody to go to the store and you give them
money, they go to the store and along the way, you know,
somebody God forbid, whatever, they get mugged. Well, of course, it's the
person who mugged them who is to blame, but then you feel
that you're to blame because you sent them on this mission, right?
So, I mean, so now everybody's sort of feeling terrible that he
died. So even the guy himself who was the guy that was
mistreated, you know, is sort of saying like, what did I do
wrong? Was there a way I could have handled that better? Was
there a way maybe, you know. A funny thing is he didn't
say that I didn't have to go to רב יוסף Rav Yosef
to complain, because that really was the more proximate sort of cause.
But anyway, but everybody is now feeling bad about this and taking
the blame. One minute. Now it gets even more interesting because now,
you know, again, like, you know, this is all the question about
how do you associate cause and effect. Just because this event happened
maybe soon before he died, was this necessarily the cause, even if
we're trying to identify the metaphysical cause of his death? Maybe there
were other things that were the cause. How do you know exactly
what things? So now everybody is going to be feeling bad about
interactions that they had with רב אדא Rav Ada saying that they
are to blame.
A Sanhedrin question now, taking us right into the middle. Exactly.
Well, to some degree, right. Okay, so גמרא says, okay, אביי Abaye
אמר, אנא ענישתי, Ana Nishtei, no, no, no, oy, I'm to blame
for the fact that he died.
דאמרו להו לרבנן עד דגרמיתו גרמי בי אביי, d'amru lehu l'rabbanan ad
d'gamrimitu garmi bei Abaye, תו אכלו בשרא שמנא בי רבא, tu achlu
bisra shamna bei Rava, because he used to tell my students, this
רב אדא, Rav Ada, remember רב אדא Rav Ada was רבא's Rava
תלמיד. talmid. He says, rather than eating the גרמי, garmi, which is
the bones, rather than chewing bones in אביי's Abaye ישיבה, yeshiva, you
should come eat some nice fat meat in רבא's Rava ישיבה. yeshiva.
So basically he was trying to steal away my students or tell
my students, you know, that they should learn by רבא Rava not
by me. Now it's so funny. So what are you to blame,
אביי? Abaye? Right? I mean, he, this רב אדא, Rav Ada, had
done something bad. He basically was, you know, was trying to tell
אביי's Abaye students, what do you want to learn from אביי? Abaye?
It's so, you know, the תורה there isn't nice and juicy, come
learn with us in רבא's Rava. ישיבה. yeshiva. So אביי Abaye says,
so again one wonders, I don't know if this is true, but
one wonders if the subtext is, you know, no, none of us
were to blame, he brought it on himself, right? So אביי Abaye
is saying, oh, I'm to blame because he said all these mean
things to my students at my ישיבה yeshiva and that's why God
punished him, so I'm to blame. Like, wait, what? Yes. That subtext.
And
רב דימי Rav Dimi makes a point to say he's from נהרדעא,
Nehardea, right? So נהרדעא Nehardea ישיבה yeshiva
from מחוזא. So it's, in other words, a competition, a commercial competition,
so now he's getting more students.
Ah, that's interesting. That's interesting. Right, right, right. That's interesting.
Yeah, people also suggest that maybe he enabled him to get to
that place where he's talking about, maybe he didn't teach him properly.
Right, but he was a student of רבא. Rava So, but maybe
you're right. Like again, it's the same way we have this tendency
to take blame for things that aren't our fault. Maybe he was
saying like, I let him do that and I never sat down
and spoke to him about it, right? I mean, you know, so
I mean, that's a way of seeing it. אביי Abaye was saying
like, I knew he was doing this and if I thought he
was doing something wrong I should have had a conversation with him
and I didn't. So it's very interesting, this like tendency to like
accept blame, okay? Although again, one does wonder if there's a subtext.
Yes.
So don't we believe that ה׳ Hashem is the one who decides
who shall live and who shall die? Yeah. And He's, ה׳ Hashem
is the final arbiter of that. So why do we take the
power of ourselves? I mean, they're not taking a knife to somebody.
Right. I mean, look, so that plays into a very important theological
issue. I mean, yes ה׳ Hashem decides, but part of the reason
ה׳ Hashem decides is because of sins that people do. So if
אביי Abaye felt that he had sinned and that this rabbi had
sinned and אביי Abaye maybe felt that he could have done something
about it, right? Or the גמרא also feels that when rabbis give
curses or say things it can bring about people's death. God allows
that to happen, right? So it's like, you know, it's the balance
of that and human responsibility. Somebody murders somebody, you say, oh, not
my... But it's not all God's responsibility that we can't take our
share of responsibility for it.
So that's one.
רבא אמר אנא ענישתיה. Rava amar ana anishteia. No, no, I'm the
one who brought about his death, who brought him to... this is
again a fascinating story where like you wonder what did רבא Rava
do wrong because when he was going to the butcher למישקל אומצא
lemishkal umtza so in order to buy a piece of meat אמר
להו לטבחי amar lehu letivchei he said to the
butchers אנא שקילנא ביסרא מקמי שמעתא דרבא. ana shakilna bisra mikamei shamtei
de-Rava. You know what? You should give me meat before you give
it to רבא'ס... Rava's... רבא Rava, had sent his attendant to go
to the butchers and this person רב אדא Rav Ada who was
a big תלמיד חכם, he was in the store and in line
next to him was רבא'ס Rava's attendant, not רבא, Rava? but רבא'ס
Rava's attendant. So he said, you know, I'm more important than רבא'ס
Rava's attendant, I should be served first, okay? ואנא עדיפנא מיניה. ve-ana
adifna minei.
Now I am better than he. Now who's the he here? Is
the he I am better than the attendant or I'm even greater
than רבא? Rava Now in the previous statement he said clearly between
me and רבא Rava there's a great gap. Okay, but anyway here
even if he meant I'm more important than the attendant, he was
basically also saying he's more important than רבא Rava. because this attendant
was representing רבא. Rava But again the question is and what did
רבא Rava do wrong here? We're actually identifying ways in רב אדא
Rav Ada maybe deserved to be punished and but they're saying I
was to blame. So again maybe רבא Rava was to blame because
he knew about this and should have said something to him. Yeah.
Whole thing, I'm thinking this whole thing is about the competition, some
kind of competition and psychology between...
Oh you mean because there you're competing of who's first in line?
רש"י also beautifully says here he says like you won't eat meat,
you'll eat what, bone, you're going to chew bones, right? רירומא לא
תשבע, reiruma lo tisba, right? Your
learning won't be satisfactory. Right, right. It's a whole thing. Yeah.
So now one last person ready to take responsibility. רב נחמן בר
יצחק אמר אנא ענישתיה. Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar ana anishteia. No,
no,
it's my fault. Why? דרב נחמן בר יצחק ריש כלה הוה. de-Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak reish kalla hava. He was the person who gave
the major שיעור shiur in the town. כלה Kalla sometimes means a
special שיעור shiur before יום טוב Yom Tov but it also could
just mean the head of the בית מדרש. Beit Midrash. כל יומא
מקמי דניעול לכלה, kol yoma mikamei deniul le-kalla,
every day before the sort of שיעור shiur started, you know they
would sort of lock the doors and begin the שיעור, shiur, מרהי
באדיה רב אדא בר אהבה לשמעתא והדר עייל לכלה. marei badeih Rav
Ada bar Ahava leshamta vehadar ayeil le-kalla.
So first רב אדא בר אהבה, Rav Ada bar Ahava, he would
use רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Ada bar Ahava as his like
prep buddy. So he was giving the שיעור shiur and he would
review what he was going to say with רב אדא בר אהבה.
Rav Ada bar Ahava. מרהי באדיה marei badeih means like he would
run through it, learn through the סוגיא sugya with רב אדא בר
אהבה Rav Ada bar Ahava to sharpen his thoughts, maybe also learn
רב אדא'ס Rav Ada's תורה or the תורה of רב that he
was communicating, and then he would go and give שיעור. shiur. So
he needed, he relied on רב אדא בר אהבה. Rav Ada bar
Ahava. ההוא יומא, Hahu yoma, a certain day, נקטוהו רב פפא ורב
הונא בריה דרב יהושע לרב אדא בר אהבה. naktuhu Rav Pappa ve-Rav
Huna breih de-Rav Yehoshua le-Rav Ada bar Ahava. So these two other
rabbis, רב פפא Rav Pappa and רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, grabbed
hold of רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Ada bar Ahava משום דלא
הוו בסיומא mishum delo havu besiyuma because they weren't at the conclusion
of a learning. Now רש"י actually says it was the סיום siyum
of מסכת בכורות Masechet Bechorot because they're actually going to be... they
actually asked him a question about
מסכת בכורות. Masechet Bechorot. Okay, remember all the בר פפא'ס Bar Pappa's
when you do a סיום, siyum, anyway so here was רב פפא
Rav Pappa and they weren't at the סיום siyum of מסכת בכורות
Masechet Bechorot and אמרו ליה, amru leih, they said to רב אדא,
Rav Ada, אימא לן הני שמעתתא דמעשר בהמה היכי אמרינהו רבא. eima
lan hanei shamata de-ma'aser behema heichi amrinhu Rava. Look,
we missed the teaching of that last perek, and this רב אדא
Rav Ada was רבא'ס Rava's student, tell us all of the חידושים
chidushim that רבא Rava had on this perek. אמר להו הכי אמר
רבא והכי אמר רבא. amar lehu hachi amar Rava vehachi amar Rava.
רבא Rava said this, רבא Rava said this. Okay, got into a
whole good געשמאק geshmak learning. אדהכי, Ada-hachi, as they were sort of
spending time reviewing what רבא Rava said, נגה ליה לרב נחמן בר
יצחק. naga leih le-Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak. It was getting late for
רב נחמן בר יצחק. Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak He, רב אדא, Rav
Ada, didn't show up for their חברותא. chavruta. רב נחמן בר יצחק
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak had to give שיעור shiur and he didn't
feel prepared for שיעור shiur because he hadn't had a chance to
learn with רב אדא. Rav Ada. Okay, so אמרו ליה רבנן לרב
נחמן בר יצחק, amru leih rabanan le-Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, so the
rabbis who were gathered to hear שיעור shiur from רב נחמן בר
יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak said to him, קום דנגה לן, kum
denaga lan, get up, give שיעור, shiur, it's getting late. למה יתיב
מר? lama yativ mar? Why are you still sitting around? Come on,
time to give שיעור. shiur. אמר להו, amar lehu, he said to
them, יתיבנא וקא מנטרנא לערסיה דרב אדא בר אהבה. yativna veka mintarna
le-arseih de-Rav Ada bar Ahava. I'm sitting and waiting to see the
coffin of רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Ada bar Ahava being brought
forth. So whoa, that was pretty... he was really angry at רב
אדא בר אהבה. Rav Ada bar Ahava. Where is he? Where is
he? Come on, I need you to help me give שיעור. shiur.
אדהכי נפק קולא דנח נפשיה דרב אדא בר אהבה. ada-hachi nafak kula
denach nafshieh de-Rav Ada bar Ahava.
So while they were in that conversation, all of a sudden an
announcement went out that רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Ada bar Ahava
had died.
ומסתברא u-mistabra now, given that so many people are willing to accept
responsibility, it actually makes sense דרב נחמן בר יצחק ענשיה, de-Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak anshieh, that it was רב נחמן Rav Nachman בר יצחק
because he specifically said I'm waiting for him to die. Although the
previous רב יוסף Rav Yosef said God should defer... defend your honor,
but that wasn't as explicit and it didn't also seem that it
was as sequential. Okay, the timing is very suggestive here, but again,
you know, it's like so and how bad was that what רב
אדא Rav Ada did here? I mean he was teaching Torah, I
mean okay he had a prior responsibility, you don't get caught up
in your teaching Torah, you can give them the שיעור shiur of
what רבא Rava said at a later time. You know that רב
נחמן is waiting for you, right? But anyway, it's pretty heavy, you
don't want to mess with these rabbis. Okay, so now the גמרא
continues. By the way, I just want to say one thing about
this impossible question he asked him about the elephant and the basket.
So תוספות Tosafot says that's actually a question in the גמרא that
the גמרא doesn't know the answer to. So what type of a
fair question was that, right? Now you could sometimes say, well I
want to see how you think about it, right? I don't want
the answer, I want to see how you think about it. Anyway,
if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, the
תוספות Tosafot essentially says at the end of the one peel, תוספות
Tosafot says like this, four lines before the bottom: וקשיא לרבינו תם
אם כן אמאי לא נקיט ליה שוקא הך בעיא דלא איפשיטא התם.
Ve'kashya le'Rabbeinu Tam im kein amai lo nakit lei shuka hach be'aya
de'la ipshita hatam. The גמרא never concludes the answer to that question
in a different גמרא. ויש לומר דמכל מקום הוה ליה לאתויי הנך
ראיות דמייתי התם ודחי להו. Ve'yesh lomar de'mikol makom hava lei le'atuyei
hanach re'ayot de'maiti hatam ve'dachi lehu. You should have at least brought
the relevant evidence. We could have had a discussion. You just said,
'I don't know!' right? Like, I mean, so you know, you can
test somebody by thinking about how they're thinking about something, even regardless
of what the answer, whether there's an answer. Yeah, I knew you'd
like that, Rabbi Ito.
Okay, so I know this is going to go really far, but
like this case of the issues of פיל שבא לקופסא. pil she'ba
le'kufsa. Yeah, isn't it similar to, you know,
אש דעלמא eish de'alma like some of the concepts?
Yeah, yeah, about how things transform.
Yeah, so there is such a conceptual framework.
Sure, yeah, absolutely. Okay, let's at least turn the page. All right,
מי שהיה כותלו סמוך לכותל חברו, Mi she'haya kotlo samuch le'kotel chaveiro,
that was too good, that was too... מי שהיה כותלו סמוך לכותל
חברו לא יסמוך לו כותל אחר אלא אם כן הרחיק ממנו ארבע
אמות. Mi she'haya kotlo samuch le'kotel chaveiro lo yismoch lo kotel acher
ela im kein hirchik mimenu arba amot. So we've seen this quoted
before. If you have your wall near your friend's wall, so don't,
if you're, meaning if you're planning, we'll see the גמרא is going
to put a sort of point out
the phrasing is a little funny. מי שהיה mi she'haya means if
you want to build a wall next to your friend's wall, then
don't put it within ארבע אמות. arba amot. Okay, even though they're
walls to your gardens or your yards and because as we'll see,
then you narrow the passageway. If it's more narrow than ארבע אמות
arba amot and nobody can pass through the two walls. That's how
the גמרא is going to explain the problem. החלונות. Ha'chalonot. Now let's
say you're at the boundary, at the borderline. Somebody's got a wall
with windows, you know, to his home, to some other structure. So
where are you going to put your wall to not block the
guy's access to the sunlight on one hand, and the other hand
is, remember the discussion at the beginning of the מסכת, Masechet,
so you don't look into his windows. All
right? So החלונות בין מלמעלה בין מלמטה בין כנגדן ארבע אמות, Ha'chalonot
bein milma'ala bein milmata bein kenegdan arba amot, four amot. Now why
you can't build it if it's higher, because if it's only a
little bit higher than the window, you can stand on the wall
and look into the guy's window. If it's a little bit lower
than the window, you can stand on the wall and look into
the window. If it's a lot lower or a lot higher, I
mean you'd have to like crane your neck, so obviously it's not
impossible necessarily, but that's a היזק ראיה hezek re'iyah story. He's got
his window way up there, now you don't have a wall, you
can't see into his second story window. You're going to build a
wall, it can't be at a height ארבע אמות arba amot in
either direction within ארבע אמות arba amot that lets you look into
his window. Now you have to be ארבע אמות arba amot away
for a different reason, so not to block the sunlight. And that's
not a lot, that's six feet. So you used to be getting
gorgeous sunlight right over here, imagine, then somebody goes ahead and builds
a wall like, you know, six feet away. So there'll be some
sunlight that'll get in, but very also depends how high the wall
is after that, right? Buildings are very high. So that seems to
be a little limit, you know, if you really still really are
encroaching, but nevertheless that's what the משנה Mishnah allows. The גמרא will
discuss other opinions. Let's just turn the page. ומי שהיה כותלו סמוך.
U'mi she'haya kotlo samuch. What do you mean? You have a wall
near your friend's wall, don't build it. It sounds like you already
had a wall. How'd you get that wall near if you're not
allowed to build it that close? So the גמרא says, אמר רב
יהודה הכי קאמר. Amar Rav Yehudah hachi ka'amar. Here's how to read
the משנה. Mishnah. הבא לסמוך לא יסמוך אלא אם כן הרחיק ממנו
ארבע אמות. Ha'ba lismoch lo yismoch ela im kein hirchik mimenu arba
amot.
If you want to build a wall, that's probably the best read
of the משנה, Mishnah, want to build a wall next to the
friend's wall, don't do it unless you have a ארבע אמות arba
amot away. Okay, this is not the windows. These are just two
walls too narrow so there's no passageway between it. מתקיף לה רבא.
Matkif lah Rava. רבא said, והמי שהיה כותלו סמוך לכותל חברו קתני.
Ve'ha mi she'haya kotlo samuch le'kotel chaveiro katani. It says you already
had the wall. It doesn't sound like you're first building it now.
אלא אמר רבא הכי קתני. Ela amar Rava hachi katani. Here's how
to read it. מי שהיה כותלו סמוך לכותל חברו בריחוק ארבע אמות.
Mi she'haya kotlo samuch le'kotel chaveiro berichuk arba amot. First it was
to code. It was ארבע אמות arba amot away, which you were
allowed to do. ונפל. Ve'nafal. Then it fell down. And now you
want to rebuild it, then לא יסמוך לו כותל אחר אלא אם
כן הרחיק ממנו ארבע אמות. lo yismoch lo kotel acher ela im
kein hirchik mimenu arba amot. Then if you want to rebuild it,
it cannot be within ארבע אמות, arba amot, it has to be
at least ארבע אמות arba amot away. Either way, nobody's really debating
the הלכה, you have to build it with ארבע אמות arba amot
away, and we'll just read one more line why, because this is
not about a window. These are two walls to two court. yards,
right? So what's the big problem having a wall right nearby? So
the גמרא says: מאי טעמא? דחשא דהכא מעלי להכא. Mai ta'ama? Dechasha
dehacha ma'ale lehacha.
Because the trampling through over there helps here. Meaning, if you keep
the space between them six feet or larger, you will have an
alleyway that people can walk through, a pathway. But we don't care
about outsiders because this is just between me and my neighbor. Why
do we have a responsibility to give outsiders a pathway? Ah, but
my neighbor wants people walking through because as you trample down, as
you walk, it hardens the ground on which the wall is built.
So right now, people can walk alongside my wall and it's good
for my wall. Don't you build something so close to my wall
that prevents that traffic and then I won't get the benefit that
I have now of people walking near my wall. Actually, it'll actually
increase the benefit if you build it because now people are very
much right in that space as opposed to having a lot of
space. Okay, so we'll see more of this tomorrow.